this is an amazing geometry question
that includes a variety of Concepts like
symmetry Circles chords and
perpendicular lines we have a circle
first we draw this chord of length five
and after that we draw this line of
length six from this point which is
perpendicular to this chord followed by
another line which is perpendicular to
this one and it is of length four now
how can we use these details to
determine the radius of this Circle can
you solve it let us start by marking the
center of this circle now in a circle
the line segment from the center that is
perpendicular to a chord will also bict
the chord this means that the
perpendicular line from the center of a
circle to its chord divides it into two
equal segments this is called chord bis
sector theorem now draw this diameter
and then draw this rectangle whose side
lengths are five and six like this now
draw this line which is perpendicular to
this side of the rectangle what do you
think its length will be since this
diameter will be perpendicular by sector
of this chord and if these are 5x two so
both of them will also be 5x two as well
and since both of these lengths are the
same therefore this segment will also be
of length four awesome now draw this
line and label it as X now we will use
another theorem called intercept in
chords theorem here is one chord of the
circle and here is another chord of the
circle so by intersecting chords theorem
this length which is 6 times this length
which is X will be the same as this
length which is four times this length
which is 5 + 4 or 9 so X will be 6
amazing now draw this line such that we
get a right triangle here what do you
think this line will be yes you you
guessed it right it will be the diameter
of this circle this is because of
thales's theorem which states that if
you draw a triangle where one of its
sides is the diameter of a circle then
the angle opposite that side is a right
angle so this hypotenuse will be 2 * the
radius R and this is 12 and this 5 so we
will now use Pythagoras Theorem such
that 2
r² = 5 S + 12 square or 25 + 144 which
is equal to 169 or 13 Square so 2 R = 13
and R = 13 by 2 and that's it wasn't
this an interesting problem were you
aware of so many theorems before this
video and able to solve it let me know
in the comments so good
[Music]